Guide to the John D. Kirkland Baker Botts public records of corporations & memorabilia, 1959-1981 MS 634
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
John D. Kirkland Baker Botts public records of corporations & memorabilia, 1959-1981
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Kirkland, John D. (David)
MS 634
17 Linear Feet 17 boxes
The John D. Kirkland Baker Botts public records of corporations & memorabilia contains bound volumes of business records and memorabilia.
Biographical Note
John David Kirkland, born 6 June 1933 in McAllen, TX, spent his formative years in Edinburg and Austin Texas. He graduated Austin High School in 1950 and attended Yale University for his Bachelor of Arts in 1955 and Yale Law School for a law degree in 1958.
Kirkland moved to Houston TX in summer 1958 to practice corporate and securities law at Baker, Botts, Shepherd & Coates, and remained until 1967. He headed the team that helped T. Boone Pickens create Mesa Petroleum Co., George H.W. Bush, founder of Zapata Corp., and J. Hugh and William Liedtke, who developed Pennzoil Co. Kirkland joined Pennzoil in 1967, served as executive vice president and member of the board of directors, and was instrumental in transforming Pennzoil into the formation that became Pogo Producing and spin-offs of United Gas and Entex. After leaving Pennzoil in 1978, he served as director of executive education at the Jones School of Management and Administration at Rice University, vice chairman of Sandefer Oil & Gas, Inc., executive vice president with Roy M. Huffington, Inc., chairman of Heritage Trust Co., director of MetFuel, Inc., chairman and chief executive officer of Antara Resources, Inc., chairman of Huntington Exploration, LLC. Kirkland had numerous ties to Houston's educational, cultural and charitable institutions.
His first marriage to Ann Wales Kirkland produced three children, and his second wife, Kate Sayen Kirkland, survived him. He died Jan. 21, 2008 and is buried at Glenwood Cemetery, Houston.
Scope and Contents
The John D. Kirkland Baker Botts public records of corporations & memorabilia contains bound volumes of business records and memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Kate Sayen Kirkland on June 22, 2015.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: Series I: Bound volumes; Series II: Memorabilia.
Index Terms
Subjects
Business
Document Types
memorabilia; legal documents
Subjects (Corporations)
Baker & Botts.
- Series I: Bound volumes
  - Tuboscope Company sale of 200,000 shares of common stock, 1959-07-22 (Box 1)
  - Alpine Geophysical Associates, Inc. registration of common stock and warrants, 1961-12-06 (Box 1)
  - Schlumberger Limited secondary offering of 700,000 shares of common stock, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Murphy Corporation: $11,500,000 principal amount, 5-3/8% promissory note due 1967-1975, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Merger of Commonwealth Oil Company with the Jupiter Corporation, 1962-03-01 (Box 1)
  - L.L. Ridgway Enterprises, Inc. sale of 170,000 shares of common stock, 1962-10-19 (Box 2)
  - Tennessee Gas Transmission Company $35,000,000 first mortgage pipeline bonds; 150,000 shares 5.04% cumulative preferred stock, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Merger of The Pennzoil Company into Pennzoil Company, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Acquistion of assets of Advanced Scientific Instruments, Inc. by Electro-Mechanical Research, Inc., 1963 (Box 2)
  - Merger of Zapata Petroleum Corporation and Stetco Petroleum Corporation into South Penn Oil Company under name of Pennzoil Company, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Houston Lighting and Power Company three-for-one stock split, 1963-05-01 (Box 3)
  - Pennzoil Company two-for-one stock split, 1964-06-12 (Box 3)
  - Mesa Petroleum Co. sale of 614,850 shares of common stock, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Tracor, Inc. sale of 110,000 shares of common stock ($ .50) par value and common stock purchase warrants (includes exhibits), 1964-10-29 (Box 3)
  - Pet Milk Company acquisition of assets of George H. Dentler and sons, 1965-01 (Box 3)
  - Vector Cable Company acquisition of assets of Marsh & Marine Manufacturing Company, Inc., 1965-03 (Box 3)
  - Mesa Petroleum co. acquisition of assets of Standard Gilsonite Company, 1965-09-10 (Box 3)
  - Tenneco Chemicals, Inc. rearrangement of long-term indebtedness, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Tennessee Gas Transmission Company $50,000,000 first mortgage pipeline bonds, 5-3/8% series due Jan. 1, 1986; 1,000,000 shares 5.36% cumulative convertible second preferred stock, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Duval Corporation sale of $25,000,000 of debentures; $13,000,000 bank loan agreements (vol. I & II), 1966-1967 (Box 4-5)
  - Pennzoil Company $135,000,000 6-1/2% notes due June 30,1968; refinancing on bank loans due Dec. 31, 166, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - Mesa Petroleum Co. sale of $4,000,000 principal amount 5-3/4% convertible subordinate debentures due 1982; original listing of debentures and common stock on the American Stock Exchange, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Murphy Oil Corporation $36,000,000 principal amount 6-1/4% promissory note due 1969-1983 (vol. I & II), 1967 (Box 5)
  - Big Three Industrial Gas & Equipment Co. sale of 150,000 shares of capital stock, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Duval Sierrita Corporation interim bank loan agreement, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc. $65,000,000 debentures 7-1/2% series due June 1, 1988; bank credit agreement; satisfaction and discharge of interim note indenture, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc. Duval exchange offer; three-for-one split; satisfaction and discharge of indenture dated as of Dec. 1, 1965, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Consolidation of Pennzoil Company (Pennzoil) and United Gas Corporation (United) to form Pennzoil United, Inc. (vol. I & II), 1968-04-01 (Box 7)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc. merger of Elk and Wolf's Head into Pennzoil; elimination of minority shareholder interest in Duval, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Duval Corporation-Bright Star Foundation, Inc. ore production payment financing, 1969-04-21 (Box 7)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc. United Gas Pipeline Company $190,299,000 debentures 4-1/8% - 5-3/4% series due July 1, 1971-June 1, 1982; $45,000,000 debentures 8-3/8% series due July 1, 1989; cancellation and discharge of line of United Mortgage, United debenture agreements and lien of pipeline mortgage (vol. I & II), 1969-07-23 (Box 8)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc. post-effective amendments to registration statements relting to $1.58-1/3 cumulative preference common stock and employees stock purchase plan, 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - United Gas Pipeline Company $15,000,000 debentures 10-1/8% series due July 1, 1990, 1970 (Box 9)
  - United Gas Pipeline Company $25,000,000 debentures 9-3/4% series due Nov. 1, 1990, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Pennzoil Offshore Gas Operators, Inc. 130,000 united comprised of $130,000,000 convertible subordinated debentures due 1979 and 4,290,000 shares of class B common stock, $1 par value, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc./United Gas, Inc. 4,056,714 shares of United common stock $5 par value; $87,000,000 6-1/2% sinking fund debentures due Dec. 31, 1979; $62,000,000 first mortgage bonds 6-1/2@ series due Dec. 31, 1989, 1970-06-30 (Box 9)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc. $75,000,000 debentures 8-3/8% series due March 1, 1996; $50,000,000 5-14% convertible subordinated debentures due 1996, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc./United Gas, Inc. $8,000,000 6-1/2% sinking fund debentures due Dec. 31, 1979; $62,000,000, 1971-02-10 (Box 10)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc./United Gas, Inc. sale of 3,044,050 shares United Gas, Inc. common stock, 1971-05-13 (Box 10)
  - Pennzoil Company post-effective amendments relating to $1.58-1/3 cumulative preference common stock and qualified and non-qualified stock option plans; registration statement relating to employees stock purchase plan; 1934 act filings, 1971-1972 (Box 10-11)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc. post-effective amendments relating to $1.58-1/3 cumulative preference common stock and employees stock purchase plan; registration statement relating to qualified stock option plan; misc. 1934 act filings, 1971-1972 (Box 11)
  - Sea Robin Pipeline Company $85,000,000 term loan notes due June 30, 1983, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Pennzoil Company bank credit agreements, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Pennzoil Company post-effective amendments relating to $1.58-1/3 cumulative preference common stock, employees stock purchase plan and qualified and nonqualified stock option plans; 1934 act filings, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
  - Pennzoil Company sale of 650,000 $8.00 cumulative preferred stock $1 par value, 1973 (Box 12)
  - Pennzoil Company merger of Pennsylvania Refining Company into Pereco, Inc., a wholly owned subsidiary of Pennzoil Company, under the name Pereco, Inc., 1973-01-26
  - Pennzoil Offshore Gas Operators, Inc. $110,000,000 production payment financing, 1973-1974 (Box 12)
  - Pennzoil Company post-effective amendments relating to employees stock purchase plan and qualified and nonqualified stock option plans; 1934 act filings, 1973-1974 (Box 12)
  - Pennzoil Company spin-off of United Gas Pipeline Company (4 volumes), 1974 (Box 13-14)
  - Pennzoil Offshore Gas Operators, Inc. $86,000,000 bank credit, 1974 (Box 14)
  - Pennzoil Louisiana and Texas Offshore, Inc. $100,000,000 bank credit, 1974 (Box 14)
  - Pennzoil Company registration statements relating to employees stock purchase plan and qualified and nonqualified stock option plans; 1934 act filings, 1974-1975 (Box 14)
  - Pennzoil Offshore Gas Operators, Inc. $120,000,000 production payment financing, 1975 (Box 15)
  - Pennzoil Company post-effective amendment relating to employees stock purchase plan and qualified and nonqualified stock option plans; 1934 act filings, 1975-1976 (Box 15)
  - Pennzoil Company $250,000,000 bank credit; $60,000,000 eurodollar borrowings, 1975-1976 (Box 15)
  - Pennzoil Offshore Gas Operators, Inc. $200,000,000 production payment financing, 1976 (Box 15)
  - Pennzoil Louisiana and Texas Offshore, Inc. $200,000,000 bank credit, 1976 (Box 16)
  - Pennzoil Company post-effective amendment relating to employees stock purchase plan and qualified and nonqualified stock option plans; 1934 act filings, 1976-1977 (Box 16)
  - Pennzoil Louisiana and Texas Offshore, Inc. $250,000,000 bank credit, 1977 (Box 16)
  - Pennzoil Company $250,000,000 bank credit, 1977 (Box 16)
  - Pennzoil Company $100,000,000 debentures 8-3/4% series due Dec. 31, 2001, 1977 (Box 16)
- Series II: Memorabilia
  - Pennzoil Company and subsidiaries evaluation of exploratory and development drilling, 1971-73, 1971-1973 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Generic model: Public works contract based on unit prices between Pemex Exploracion y Produccion and [contractor], 2003-06 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Development of low cost industrial and strategic raw materials: a proposal, 1969-11-19 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Performance Unlimited, Inc. board of director's meeting minutes, by-laws, 1964 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Pennzoil United, Inc. stock certificate, 1971-03-30 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Photographs
    - Huffco Indonesia receptions, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - United Gas Corporation Mortgage and Deed of Trust R.I.P. album (Box 17)
    - Albums [2 together]: Pertamina/Huffco IJV Group Executive Management Seminar (Box 17)
  - Paperweights/lucite enclosed announcements/prospectus
    - Pennzoil Offshore Gas Operators, Inc. $2000,000,000 production payment financing, 1976-11-23 (Box 17)
    - Pennzoil Louisiana and Texas Offshore, Inc. $130,000,000 convertible subordinated debentures due 1979 and 5,200,000 shares of class B common stock, 1972-08-16 (Box 17)
    - Pennzoil Company debentures 10-5/8% series due May 1, 1983, 1975-05-08 (Box 17)
    - Pennzoil Company sale of 650,000 shares $8.00 cumulative preferred stock, 1973-05-10 (Box 17)
    - Badak LNG sales contract, 1980-04 (Box 17)